Guide to the Arthur L. Dahl Papers, 1900-1939 JL022
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Arthur L. Dahl Papers,
1900-1939
JL022
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
3.5 Linear feet
Arthur L. Dahl held various positions in the United States Civil Service, among them personal secretary to Gifford Pinchot, who was then National Forester. Dahl was transferred to San Francisco in 1908 as Chief of Maintenance in the Bureau of Forestry District #5. By 1918 he had quit the civil service and was involved in the oil business.
Dahl, Arthur L., 1880-1952
Biography
1880, Oct. 16 Born in Port Leavenworth, Kansas.
1900, Dec. 17 Becomes stenograher for George Wright, U.S. Indian Inspector for Indian Territory at Muscogee.
1901, Dec. Passes Civil Service Stenographer and Typewriter test.
1902, Dec. Post Office Department.
1903, Dec. 26 Bureau of Forestry, Department of Agriculture as Clerk, Stenographer and Typewriter. Becomes personal secretary of Gifford Pinchot.
1905, June Graduated with Bachelor of Laws degree from George Washington University.
1905 Involved in oil - member of Santa Paula Oil Association, Secretary of Willard Canyon Oil Co., Director of Climax Oil Co.
1923 Involved with Insurance Exchange, S.F.
1927 With Hammon Engineering Co., S.F.
1932 With Life Department of the Aetna Life Insurance Co.
1933, Aug Appointed Secretary and returns to former work as Pacific Coast correspondent and representative of several trade publications.
1952 (?) Year of death.
Scope and Content
The collection, which was given by his son, consists of some correspondence and documents relating to his early civil service jobs, his oil associations and his position with the Insurance Broker's Exchange. However, the great majority of the collection is lists and copies of articles that Dahl had published in various magazines and other periodicals between 1910 and 1937. Writing was a profitable hobby, at which he spent his spare hours from his business career. The articles range from highly technical articles about agricultural machines and methods to anecdotes with morals. In some cases the entire periodical, in which an article by Dahl is reproduced, has been preserved, and they provide interesting and rare reading material. A Good example of this is the issues of Grit dated from 1916 to 1925.
Provenance
Gift of Arthur L. Dahl, Jr. to the Jackson Library of Business, 1972. Transferred to Special Collections in 1979.
Access Restrictions
None.
United States. Forest Service--Officials and employees.; Articles.; Business records.; Petroleum industry and trade.
- Correspondence re: Dahl Collection (JL022) (Box 1)
- George Washington University Graduation (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Civil Service Papers and Correspondence, 1900 Dec - 1908 Oct (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains letters to and from Congressman and other government bureaucrats concerning changes in Dahl's job (switches position, agency or Department).
- Oil Stock: Willard Canyon Co., Kimerick Co. and Santa Paula Oil Association, 1916 Jan - 1927 Sept (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Contains stock certificates, correspondence and contracts concerning these three companies. Dahl was an officer (Secretary) of Willard and Santa Paula.
- Albert E. Boynton and Wendell C. Hammon (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Contains a biography of Boynton written by Dahl; and memorandums, written by Dahl, noting that he had served as a witness to the wills of both of these men, who were business associates (oil) and friends.
- Insurance Broker's Exchange, 1933 Sept - 1936 Aug (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Contains articles giving a brief biography of Dahl upon the occasion of his appointment as Secretary of the Exchange; then one letter and clippings of articles regarding his resignation from that same position.
- Lists of Articles Published, 1910 - 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Is a handwritten list of articles found in the bound volumes: JL022 Box 1 Folders 2 - 3.
- Copy of Correspondence concerning article titled VICTORY DOCK SEAMEN (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Original and Carbon Copies of Submitted Articles (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Most of these articles were rejected by publishers, N.D.
- Horst's Evaporated Vegetables (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes diffferent articles and brochures written by Dahl about evaporated vegetables, and correspondence from E. Clemens Horst about the articles.
- Loose Articles, 1916 - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Folder containg about ten articles from different magazines on vastly different subjects.
- Articles, Arthur L. Dahl, 1914 - 1921 (Box 2)
  Contains various articles, the majority of which are about Forestry and Agriculture in various magazines (including Scientific American, American Thresherman, and Farm Power,etc.). Arranged in groups of same magazine, chronologically within each group.
- Articles, Arthur L. Dahl, 1917 - 1937 (Box 3)
  Contents and manner of arrangement greatly similar to JL022 Box # 2. Different periodicals included: Pacific Ports, Automatic World, Tractor and Gas Engine Review, Grit, The Independent, Masonite Publications, etc. Dates: 1917 - 1937.
- Various Magazine Issues with Articles by Arthur Dahl, 1911 July - 1936 Dec (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Contents vary but predominantly the articles are concerned with agricultural and technical topics. Periodicals: Technical World, Overland Monthly, Munsey's Magazine, Masonite Publications, etc. Dates range: 1911 July - 1936 Dec. Note: Overland Monthly - 1923 July contains: 1. Eulogy of Jane Lathrop Stanford and 2. an article about the Hoover Library, neither written by Dahl.
- Grit (Williamsport Pa.), 1916 Nov - 1925 Jan (Box 4, Folder 2)
- The Philidelphia Record, 1917 Mar 4 - 1918 Dec 22 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Various issues with articles by Dahl.
- Various newspapers, 1910 Sept 10 - 1921 Oct 25 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Including N.Y. Times, L.A. Times and others with articles by Dahl.
- Scrapbook, 1907 - 1916 (Box 5)
  Articles written by Dahl.
- Scrapbook, 1916 - 1920 (Box 6)
- Scrapbook, 1921 - 1925 (Box 7)